Doom scrolling on mute has made us
forget how powerful sound really is
pretty visuals grab your attention but
it sound that keeps you
hooked I'm going to share the three
sound design techniques that took me 16
years to master but it only take you a
few minutes to learn using these three
alone will instantly upgrade your work
but for each technique I'm going to
share a secret cheat code that made the
biggest difference in my work so you
won't want to miss any of
these my sound effects used to sound
really flat and boring it wasn't
necessarily the sounds that I used but
it was how I used it now the best
example I can give is a whoosh a single
whoosh can be okay for matching visuals
of a small
movement but when there's a big dramatic
one a single whoosh isn't quite enough
finding a deeper whoosh will help but
still lacks
weight thinking about sounds in
different frequencies is what solved the
problem
[Music]
so imagine layering a cake where each
layer adds a unique flavor except on an
audio Spectrum it looks more like this
now by layering sounds with different
frequencies you can achieve a much more
full Dynamic
Sound instead of scrolling endlessly for
the right sound effects thinking in
layers puts you miles ahead now the
cheat code for using this technique is
applying it outside of sound effects
like with your dialogue and your music I
used to throw my dialog track right onto
my timeline and then lower the gain of
my background music and just call it a
day but ever since I saw a tutorial from
my buddy Dave I've been using this
technique he shared in every video I've
ever edited since I've learned it
instead of using the DSR effect for its
intended purpose you can use it to carve
out a pocket in the mid- frequencies of
your music
track your dialogue naturally sits in
that pocket and you can always EQ it to
cut off the low and high ends for a
better fit but this technique gives each
element its own space resulting in a
fuller mix a lot of you have asked me
where I get my sound effects from and my
go-to answer has always been art list
but a secret weapon I've been using for
years is soundpacks from Happy editing
I'm really excited that the sponsoring
this video and I want to show you how I
use their packs to make my videos stand
out first let's have a listen of this
promo cut using sound effects that's
scattered across different sources and
genres
[Music]
so it sounds pretty good but it does
feel a little bit safe because I'm using
the same set of sounds that I would for
any video I work on having a broad
library of sound effects is amazing when
you're working on a lot of different
genres of videos but if you're working
on an athletic commercial and you're
using the same sound effects that you
would for a wedding video or corporate
video you're not going to get the best
results now let's replace the sounds
with ones from Happy editing's
transition sound effects pack this pack
covers all the category of sounds that I
frequently use when I'm editing like
risers hits and whooshes especially
whooshes let's take a
listen he the difference the sound
matches the visual aesthetic and feels
way more coherent and that's the main
tip that I want to share commit to a
style instead of mixing random sounds
gritty Basse hits aren't going to work
for your corporate videos the same way
clean bell dings won't work for your
street wear promo soundpacks have been
the easiest way for me to keep my style
consistent or to keep a specific video
feeling consistent most of the Glitchy
sound effects that you hear in my work
have been from Happy editing so if you
like the sounds that you heard check out
this transition sound effects pack with
the link below huge thank you to happy
editing for sponsoring this video
keeping this tip in mind the cheat code
I'll sometimes use to make my video
Stand Out is using sounds that do not
not match the visuals this was inspired
by the show Euphoria where the director
uses something they call emotional
realism the cinematography on the show
portrays how the characters feel in
their environment rather than what's
literally happening I took that same
principle and applied it to sound design
so in a video I made called The Vessel
and the filter it's just shots of me
making coffee but the message is how
making coffee is similar to our creative
process as filmmakers to add more weight
to the visuals I replac the literal
sounds with only nature sounds coffee
grounds breaking became the crackling of
icebergs and the swish of coffee
transformed into an ocean
crash by limiting myself to only nature
sounds and intentionally mismatching the
visuals you can create a deeper
experience for your audience okay so
let's say you're editing a 30second
promo video and you want to use a song
that's 3 minutes how do you cut the
music to fit in that video length I had
a lot of trouble trimming Down music
when I first started because ending a
song early felt like just driving and
then suddenly slamming my brakes the
remix feature in premere does a pretty
good job but most of the time I need
more control to fit the visuals or to
emphasize key moments so after watching
endless amounts of movie trailers and
promo videos I'm going to share my
favorite way to transition in and out of
a song If the song you're using doesn't
have a natural lead
in you can use the beginning beat of the
song Reverse it and use it as a riser to
naturally ease into the
song If the beginning beat doesn't work
you can always try reversing the tail
end of the song to use as a riser as
well this method is a great way to
introduce a new song in the same video
or to get back into a song after a
bridge or a quiet moment of the
[Applause]
song now the way that I like to get out
of a song is adding a Reverb on the
final beat all I do is cut before the
next beat hits cut the beginning of the
beat Nest it extend the nested sequence
by placing something else further down
the timeline in this case I just
duplicate that section disable it and
move it down further so we don't hear it
a second time and then I go back to the
main timeline and add a studio Reverb on
it you can play with different presets
to find the best fit but usually I like
to start out with the Great Hall preset
this is without the
[Music]
Reverb and this is with the
Reverb sometimes I'll do a little fade
at the end of the original track and
then play the Reverb version underneath
like this
using these two methods already gets you
great and natural sounding results but
the cheat code that I use to make it
feel absolutely seamless is layering
sound effects on top of these methods so
to ease into a track I look for sounds
like risers swells or suckback to layer
underneath like
this they're also great for getting out
of a song to emphasize moments in your
videos like
this I don't know if you noticed but you
got a crack in your windshield if you
want the ending of your song to hit
harder don't be afraid to add these
sounds as well and even impacts slams or
hits to wrap it all up with a
bang the quality of my sound design
improved drastically after applying
these three techniques so let me know in
the comments if they helped you as well
[Music]